Good morning. Today's דף daf is כ"ז, Chaf Zayin, 27, and we
will be finishing the second פרק perek and beginning the third.
It would be nice if these פרקים perakim were a little bit—I
mean, as we mentioned I think on the first day, the מסכת
masechet is very well structured in that the first פרק perek opens
up with כללים klalim and then we focus in on שן shen
and רגל regel and so on. But once we get to the
individual division of the פרקים, perakim, they're not as sort of single-topic
as we would like. So while the second פרק perek was dominated
the discussions of שן shen and רגל, regel, by the end we
were dealing with what's a שור מועד shor muad and what's a
שור תם. shor tam. We sort of started that discussion, we're going
to go back to that discussion. We also had the whole issue
about,
about what do you call it, about
קרן ברשות הניזק, keren b'reshut hanizak, right? The מחלוקת machloket רבי טרפון
Rabbi Tarfon and רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, when it does a קרן
keren in a private domain, is that going to be half damages
or full damages? And now we have אדם מועד לעולם. adam muad
l'olam. So to remind you why we're doing that, that was all
an elaboration of the end of the first פרק perek where it
said there are five מועדים. muadim. Remember five מועדים? muadim? שן shen
and רגל regel and קרן ברשות הניזק keren b'reshut hanizak and אדם
adam and I missed one. Anyway, so there are those—oh, and of
course a שור המועד. shor hamuad. So this פרק perek elaborated on
those five מועדים. muadim. It was a dominant discussion of שור מועד,
shor muad, but it was also like a little bit of a
tease because it began the whole discussion of תם tam and מועד
muad and three times and reversing it, but it never didn't fully
flesh that out. And in a similar way, we are now finishing
up the discussion of אדם מועד לעולם, adam muad l'olam, which interestingly
also continues into the next פרק, perek, and then we'll sort of
see what the next פרק perek consists of. Okay,
but just to sort of make you aware that we've dealt with
some major discussions of some of those distinct categories, but we're sort
of beginning those discussions to be more fully fleshed out later. And
now we're in the middle of the discussion of אדם מועד לעולם.
adam muad l'olam. So what the גמרא Gemara said is made a
very important point at the very beginning. It talked about a person
sleeping who accidentally breaks a vessel or blinds somebody else's eye. And
the גמרא Gemara said this idea of אדם מועד לעולם adam muad
l'olam that you always pay full regardless of negligence is only for
נזק, nezek, is only for damages. But in terms of the additional
payment that a person pays in cases of personal injury, like שבת
shevet and ריפוי ripuy and בושת boshet and צער, tza'ar, all those
cases of personal injury, that you would not pay at all times.
You would only pay when? What would be the circumstances under which
you would pay that? So the גמרא Gemara did not fully spell
that out. רש"י, Rashi, to remind you, רש"י Rashi at the bottom
of כ"ו עמוד א' Chaf Vav Amud Aleph says דלא מחייב ארבעה
דברים אלא ומזיד או קרוב למזיד דומיא דחבונא דאנשים דהתם כתיב ריפוי
ושבת. d'lo mechayev arba'ah devarim ela u'meizid o karov l'meizid, dumiya d'chabuna
d'anashim, d'hasam ksiv ripuy v'shevet.
He discusses a—the פסוק pasuk says when people are fighting and it
talks about רק שבתו יתן
ורפא ירפא. rak shivto yiten v'rapo yerape. So you're fighting, you're intentionally
trying to inflict damage. So he says it has to be therefore
be you're not מועד לעולם muad l'olam those additional payments, but you
don't have to be really fully מתכוון, mitkaven, רש"י's Rashi's phrase is
fully intentional to do damage, he says רש"י's Rashi's phrase is מזיד,
meizid, intentional, או קרוב למזיד, o karov l'meizid, close to מזיד. meizid.
So this is what we are now going to sort of turn
to right now to identify what is the threshold under which you
would pay those additional payments beyond נזק. nezek. And yesterday we looked
at some scenarios where which would seem to be a good degree
of negligence that you would not. Somebody shoots an arrow and he
wants it to go a certain distance and it goes a longer
distance and injures somebody, right? I think that's probably the best example
of a degree of negligence. What are you doing shooting an arrow
in that person's
direction? And nevertheless, that's not considered negligent enough or קרוב למזיד karov
l'meizid enough to pay ארבעה דברים. arba'ah devarim. People remember that from
yesterday? That I think was the most—another case was you're lying on
a rooftop sunning yourself and you have a rock on you and
you knew you had a rock on you and you forgot about
it and then you stood up. Okay, but even that, way pretty
negligent forgetting you have a rock on you when you're sunning yourself
on a rooftop. But even that is like not as much negligence
as shooting an arrow and expecting it to go some distance and
it goes a further distance. And nevertheless it said in that case
you're exempt on the ארבעה דברים. arba'ah devarim. So let's keep that
in mind because now we're going to try to see the threshold
of when you are חייב chayav in these extra payments for personal
injury. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara picks up like this.
בשור, Bashore, two lines down on כ"ז עמוד א', Chaf Zayin Amud
Aleph, right? We read ודאמר רב מסא בשם רב אחיסאי מחייב מסיסו.
Vid'amar Rav Mesa b'shem Rav Achisai mechayev meisiso. Yes? Okay,
so בשור, Bashore, now this is a—these are sort of statements of
רבא. Rava. רבא Rava had some or רבה Rabba some great statements
about throwing a vessel off of a rooftop and somebody coming and
removing the pillows from underneath that they both are exempt. The guy
who threw it, it was going to land on a pillow, he
didn't do anything; the guy who removed the pillow, he was indirect.
Or if you threw a vessel off of a rooftop and it
was going to hit the ground and somebody broke it, the second
person is exempt because the thing was already about to break. Presumably,
the first person would
be... Now בר שדא דקיבלה בקרנו, bar shada de-kibla be-karnov, somebody threw
a baby off of a rooftop and an ox came and gored
it in mid-air. Okay? So פלוגתא דרבי ישמעאל בנו של יוחנן בן
ברוקא ורבנן. plugta de-Rabbi Yishmael beno shel Yochanan ben Beroka ve-Rabbanan. Does
the- do you have to pay כופר kofer in that case for,
you know, killing a person? If the ox has gored three times,
you pay כופר, kofer, would there be a כופר kofer payment in
that case? דתניא, de-tanya, we learned in a ברייתא, brayta, ונתן פדיון
נפשו, ve-natan pidyon nafsho, that you shall pay the redemption of the
soul, this case of כופר, kofer, when your ox gores and kills
somebody. דמי ניזק, demei nizak, the- you pay for the life as
it would be marked as sold in the slave market of the
person whose life was killed, or the- it's funny he calls it
ניזק, nizak, but it means דמי נהרג. demei neherag. רבי ישמעאל בנו
של יוחנן בן ברוקא אומר דמי מזיק. Rabbi Yishmael beno shel Yochanan
ben Beroka omer: demei mazik. No, the owner of the ox pays
for the value of his life, how much he would be sold
in the slave market. Because here's the idea: if you're paying an
atonement payment, the חידוש chiddush of the תורה Torah by an ox
that gores somebody is that as opposed to in the ancient world
where the הלכה halacha was that if an ox gored somebody there
would be times where actually you would take the life for the
owner. By the way, it explains the פסוק, pasuk, right? The פסוק
pasuk says או בן יגח או בת יגח כמשפט הזה יעשה לו.
o ben yigach o bat yigach ke-mishpat ha-zeh ye’aseh lo. Right? Everybody
knows that one by the ox that gores somebody. So what do
you mean if it kills
a boy or a girl? Like why do I need that פסוק?
pasuk? Of course it'll be the same, because in the ancient world
if it would kill- if ראובן's Reuven ox would kill
שמעון's Shimon children then they would kill ראובן's Reuven children. So as
the פסוק pasuk is saying: no, no, no, no, no. You do
not take the life of the owner or the owner’s children. What
you do is you pay a כופר. kofer. Okay? So the כופר,
kofer, because it’s an atonement payment for the loss of the life,
how do you make that atonement payment? One way to say is
you try to do something that symbolically is giving back the life
of the one who was killed. So that would be the value
of that
person’s way you would assign a value to human life of course,
which is absurd, but the only way we can do it is
we do it based on how it would go in the slave
market. But the other way of understanding it is not giving back
the value of the life that was taken, but giving the value
of the life of the person who owned the ox, because it’s
a statement that his life deserves to be taken, and instead of
taking his life, you’re taking something to substitute for his life. You’re
taking a monetary payment. Okay? So therefore, if that’s so that’s the
debate. So now we’re saying that that would tie in here. Why
would that tie in here? Because this baby thrown off the roof,
it doesn’t have any value in the slave market. Right? Who’s going
to pay for a baby that’s about to die as it hits
the ground? So if you pay דמי ניזק, demei nizak, you wouldn’t
pay anything. But if you pay דמי מזיק, demei mazik, then you’re
obviously then you’re going to pay however much the value of the
owner of the ox is. Okay? So in that case, the baby
thrown off the roof that the ox gores and kills, it would
whether there would be a payment or not would depend on דמי
ניזק demei nizak versus דמי מזיק. demei mazik. Okay. ואמר רבה, ve-amar
Rabba, now רבה Rabba says, now this gets us back to
the
case of as I was saying about what is the threshold of
payment for personal injury, for חבלה. chabalah. ואמר רבה: ve-amar Rabba: נפל
מראש הגג, nafal me-rosh ha-gag, oh, excuse me, we’re not there yet.
First we have to have this one case. נפל מראש הגג ונתקע
באשה. nafal me-rosh ha-gag ve-nitka be-ishah.
Oh, actually it is, it’s both. Okay. A person falls off of
a rooftop and happens to have an erection while he’s at the
rooftop and he winds
up penetrating, thank you, a woman. Okay? This is like the when
you’re teaching this in a high school, this is the case that
you never forget. Okay, anyway, the kids will never forget this case.
Exactly how the גמרא Gemara imagined that this could actually happen I
don’t know, but anyway. חייב בארבעה דברים, chayav be-arba'ah devarim,
well, we’re going to get to that. חייב בארבעה דברים- chayav be-arba'ah
devarim but why is it לאו מעשה? lav ma'aseh? We’ll see in
a minute. חייב בארבעה דברים ובביאה לא קנה. chayav be-arba'ah devarim u-ve-viah
lo kanah. So now finally after having all those cases where you’re
exempt from ארבעה דברים arba'ah devarim because you were not negligent enough,
even the shooting of the arrow case, here all of a sudden
you’re חייב chayav in ארבעה דברים. arba'ah devarim. But you’re not חייב
chayav but it would not be an act of sex to make
this woman your
wife, if it was his sister-in-law and the brother had died. I
understand. So let’s read what the גמרא Gemara says. חייב בנזק בצער
ריפוי ובשבת. chayav be-nezek be-tza'ar ripuy u-ve-shevet. Now first of all you’re
חייב chayav in four of five, נזק צער ריפוי ושבת, nezek tza'ar
ripuy ve-shevet, אבל בושת לא, aval boshet lo, not בושת. boshet. דתנן
de-tnan because we taught in the משנה: mishnah: אינו חייב על הבושת
עד שמתכוון. eino chayav al ha-boshet ad she-mitkavein. You have to actually
have intention. Negligence isn’t enough. בושת boshet you really need intention. We’ll
see about that in a minute. But by these other things, negligence
is enough. Now we have a double problem understanding what we just
taught because number one is why is this more negligent than the
case of the shooting of the arrow? Right? That’s not clear at
all. Now you could- say that maybe it has to do with
the fact that the, that the guy has the
erection because הנאה שלא לדעת Hana'ah shelo loda'at there's a general understanding
that, right, that if I mean the relevance of that is that
you know the assumption that an erection happens only if the person
wants it, you know, which is interesting because it doesn't really pay
attention to the sort of like, you know, a physiological response to
you know being sexually stimulated even if it's not like your desire
to have it. But anyway, but the גמרא Gemara but the גמרא
Gemara nevertheless says that and that's relevant in the following case. Let's
say somebody says to someone kill this person or I'll kill you.
Right? So you're supposed to let so you're supposed to let yourself
be killed. But let's say the person didn't do that and he
went ahead and he killed the guy that he was you know
the guy that he was told to kill. Has he committed murder?
Is he liable for an act of murder? So the הלכה Halacha
is the way the רמב"ם Rambam and תוספות Tosafot rule is that
you're not this guy is not liable for an act of murder.
He did the act of murder under duress. So what did he
do wrong then? What he did wrong was that he did not
do he did not fulfill the מצוה Mitzvah of to of of
יהרג ואל יעבור Yehareg v'al ya'avor of you know of קידוש השם
Kiddush Hashem of giving up the life before doing that. But but
the act of murder itself was an act that was done under
duress and he has not violated the act of murder. Now let's
say somebody says to this person you know have sex with this
married woman or I'll kill you. And he's supposed to give up
his life because one of the יהרג ואל יעבור Yehareg v'al ya'avor
is forbidden acts of sex and he doesn't and he has sex
with that woman. So in that case he is liable for having
done an act of adultery. It's not considered to be under duress
and not really his act. Why? Because there's a principle of אין
קישוי אלא לדעת. Ein kishuy ella loda'at. That since erection ultimately comes
because a person like wants to have it then the source of
the desire and the want for the act when you're somebody is
murdering somebody under duress the source of the desire for the act
is seen to be external to him and being imposed upon him.
When in this case the source of the desire for the act
is seen to be internal to him. Okay that's this principle of
אין קישוי אלא לדעת. Ein kishuy ella loda'at. So you could have
sort of said that maybe that somehow explains this case and since
this case is this guy with this erection so maybe it's considered
considered to be like his act and not an accident and fundamentally
you know that he wanted it. Of course if that's true then
he'd be liable in both and anyway if that were true you'd
also be it should be an act of יבום Yibum it should
be an act of making his you know of sex that his
sister-in-law is now his wife. So that doesn't seem to be the
way to go. So let's see what רש"י Rashi says. רש"י Rashi
says ונתקע באשה u'nitka b'ishah this is רש"י Rashi two lines three
lines down in the narrow lines ונתקע באשה חייב ארבעה דברים וכגון
u'nitka b'ishah chayav arba'ah devarim u'kegon רש"י Rashi says שנפל ברוח מצויה
דהוי ליה קרוב למזיד. she'nafal b'ruach metzuyah de'havei leh karov l'mezid.
So רש"י Rashi says no the only reason here this is considered
negligent is because the guy was standing at the edge of the
roof and he should have expected that it was very likely that
he would fall. So then why does it not work for the
case of יבום? Yibum? וביבמתו לא קנה אף על פי ששנינו הבא
על יבמתו בין בשוגג בין במזיד קנה u'v'yevimto lo kanah af al
pi she'shaninu haba al yevimto bein b'shogeg bein b'mezid kanah
that if a man has sex with his sister-in-law it creates an
act of יבום Yibum whether it's intentional or not intentional. הני מילי
היכא דנתכוון לשום הני מילי דנתכוון לביאת אשה אחרת. hani milei heicha
d'nitkaven l'shum hani milei d'nitkaven l'biat ishah acheret.
That's when he wants to have sex, he just thought the woman
he was having sex with was a different woman. But it was
an intentional act of sex. אבל לא נתכוון לשום ביאה aval lo
nitkaven l'shum biah this case he wasn't intending to have an act
of sex הילכך לא קנה. hilkach lo kanah. Okay and therefore it
does not work. So רש"י Rashi says that this has nothing that
this is not because of this issue of the קישוי kishuy of
the erection basically this person it was all an accident and that's
why since it was not an intended act of sex it doesn't
work for יבום Yibum so then why do you pay ארבעה דברים?
arba'ah devarim? So רש"י Rashi just says רוח מצויה. ruach metzuyah. It
was a high degree of negligence. Okay רוח מצויה ruach metzuyah a
common wind it would have been likely to expect that's a degree
of negligence for example that a שומר חינם shomer chinam is חייב
chayav for. So what you have to do now is you have
to go back to everything we talked about yesterday and say that
the guy who forgets that he has the rock on his chest
or the guy who shoots an arrow to go two feet and
goes four feet or four feet and goes eight feet you have
to say oh that wasn't negligent enough. Okay that was a middle
degree of negligence. But once you hit high degree of negligence רוח
מצויה ruach metzuyah then that's what you're חייב chayav for
for ארבעה דברים arba'ah devarim for the other payments for personal injury
with the exception of בושת. boshet. בושת boshet needs intention and now
we're going to look at that in a minute. Yes.
Wait so in the case of this guy you know he is
thinking sexual thoughts so he is thinking about it?
Okay but that doesn't mean that he's negligent for the person standing
below or whatever. Oh you mean in terms of יבום? Yibum? But
he's not trying to have sex with this woman?
Oh you should actually try to have sex.
Yeah the act he thought he was doing wasn't an act of
sex. Correct correct. Hillel you had a question?
I was wondering about how this
goes back to Oh,
that's an interesting question.
Would you have תחילתו בפשיעה וסופו באונס t'chilato bipshia v'sofo b'ones in
terms of ארבעה דברים? arba devarim?
Yeah, that's an interesting question.
Yeah, I understand the question. Like let's say, I mean since we're
going on the משנה Mishna that says that he's lied down next
to a person,
right? סימא עין חברו, sima ein chaveiro, he's פטור, pattur, right? And
based on the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, whatever, תוספות Tosafot points out that that's
like, that's the person came and lied down, I'm sorry, he's חייב
chayav by סימא
עין חברו.
sima ein
chaveiro. Yeah. No, wait.
Yeah, I don't know, it's a good question what you do תחילתו
בפשיעה וסופו באונס. t'chilato bipshia v'sofo b'ones.
I don't know. Okay, we'll have to think about that. All right,
so let's take a look now as the גמרא Gemara continues. All
right, so ואמר רבה v'amar Rava now בשת boshet that you have
to be מתכוין. mitkavein. בשת boshet אלא ela בשת. boshet. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this: ואמר רבה, v'amar Rava, and רבה Rava
says, now we're going to clarify a little bit about this מתכוין
mitkavein by בשת. boshet. נפלה מראש הגג ברוח שאינה מצויה, nafla merosh
hagag beruach she'eina metzuya, and here's where you see where רש״י Rashi
got the רוח מצויה. ruach metzuya. If the guy fell off with
an unexpected wind, unexpected doesn't necessarily mean it's an אונס, ones, it
could be but not like it's not blatant negligence, not gross negligence,
okay, ברוח שאינה מצויה beruach she'eina metzuya והזיק ובייש, veheizeik uveiyeish, and
he damaged somebody below and he caused them to be embarrassed, חייב
על הנזק, chayav al hanezek, he's חייב chayav for נזק nezek because
אדם מועד לעולם, adam muad l'olam, ופטור מארבעה דברים, upattur me'arba devarim,
and he's exempt with the four extra payments for personal injury because
we said you need פשיעה pshia and רוח שאינה מצויה ruach she'eina
metzuya is not
פשיעה. pshia. ופטור מארבעה דברים. upattur me'arba devarim. Now, ופטור מארבעה דברים.
upattur me'arba devarim. Now, ברוח מצויה, beruach metzuya, and here it's even
more explicit where רש״י Rashi is getting that as the standard. If
it was a wind that could be expected, והזיק ובייש, veheizeik uveiyeish,
and he caused personal damage and embarrassed somebody, חייב בארבעה דברים, chayav
be'arba devarim, he pays four things. So here you see the level,
the threshold to be חייב chayav for the payments of personal injury
is רוח מצויה, ruach metzuya, which means sort of פשיעה, pshia, the
type of gross negligence שומר חינם shomer chinam is חייב chayav for,
ופטור על הבשת, upattur al haboshet, but exempt for the בשת boshet
because even with this gross negligence, that is not intentional. And בשת
boshet you're only חייב chayav if you're intending to actually embarrass or
to injure. As we're going to, and then that's the last line,
נתהפך חייב אף על הבשת. nithapeich chayav af al haboshet. But if
the guy is in midair turned around, like he flipped over because
he figured, as רש״י Rashi explains it, he'd rather fall on somebody
below than fall on the concrete. So he intentionally sort of tried
to move his position in midair to fall on that person. Then
that's going to be considered enough כוונה kavana to be חייב chayav
on בשת. boshet. Okay, which is, now that's a חידוש chiddush because
there's two things. Well, maybe, that's an interesting question. I don't know,
it's an interesting question, but or maybe, but the point is there's
a double חידוש chiddush here. Number one is you're not intending to
injure the, to embarrass the guy below, you're just trying to break
your fall. Not only are you not intending to embarrass the guy
below, you're not even trying to hurt him. You don't have any
ill-will towards that person. But you're, but just again, you're just trying
to save yourself. But nevertheless, since this act which is intended to
save yourself is going to come at the, you know that you
are going to injure him or might injure him in the process,
that's considered to be intending to injure him. And as we're about
to see, if you intend to injure even if you don't intend
to embarrass, that is the level you need to be חייב chayav
for בשת. boshet. דתניא, detanya, we learned in a ברייתא, braita, ממשמע
שנאמר. mimashma shene'emar.
Now the פסוק pasuk we learn בשת boshet from is a case
where the woman intervenes with her husband and another man fighting, and
it says, you know, she grabs him in the genitals or the
other man, and it says you cut off her hand. So the
Rabbis say they don't literally mean you cut off her hand, it
means she pays for the embarrassment. ושלחה ידה והחזיקה, v'shalcha yada v'hechezika,
she sent forth her hand, איני יודע שהחזיקה, eini yodeia shehechezika,
of course she therefore grabbed the guy. Why did it have to
say that? I don't know, yeah, I don't know exactly understand the
question. But anyway, מה תלמוד לומר והחזיקה, ma talmud lomar v'hechezika,
she grabbed hold of the guy, לומר לך lomar lach כיון שנתכוין
להזיק, keivan shenitkavein lehazik,
since she was trying to damage, אף על פי שלא נתכוין לבייש,
af al pi shelo nitkavein levayeish, even though you were not trying
to embarrass, you were just trying to ושלחה ידה, v'shalcha yada, like
just trying to, you know, to injure the person or to intervene
and not strictly be trying to cause embarrassment, okay, that is enough
intention in order to be חייב chayav for בשת. boshet. So for
בשת boshet you need not, negligence is not enough, you need כוונה,
kavana, but כוונה kavana not to cause embarrassment, כוונה kavana to do
damage. And the חידוש chiddush of the case of the guy flipping
in midair is he might be intending to injure but he's not
motivated to injure the guy. He doesn't want to injure the guy.
But he's doing an act that he knows will or might very
likely bring about injury. And that also is considered sufficient. So to
do an act that you know might very well injure this person,
that is considered כוונה להזיק kavana lehazik and that is considered enough
to be חייב chayav for בשת. boshet. Okay, so those are the
thresholds. נזק nezek is even אונס. oness. שבת ריפוי צער shevet ripuy
tza'ar is פשיעה, p'shiah, the type of פשיעה ברוח מצויה p'shiah beruach
metzuya the ראשונים rishonim talk about for. בושת boshet is כוונה, kavannah,
but not כוונה לבייש, kavannah levayesh, כוונה להזיק, kavannah lehazik, and כוונה
להזיק kavannah lehazik is even if you don't want to hurt, you
know you don't want to hurt the person, but you basically are
doing an act that you know is going to hurt the person
or might very well hurt the person. What? Yeah. Now ואמר רבא
ve'amar Rava
הניח לו גחלת על לבו heniach lo gachelet al libo let's say,
okay, a lot of funny like, you know, רבא Rava has a
lot of these nice scenarios here all lined up. Somebody put a
coal on another person's, like a burning ember on somebody else's heart,
like guy was lying on the floor, ומת umet and the person
died as a result, פטור. patur. So it's not an act of
murder, you're exempt, and maybe also exempt even if it was for
גלות galus because the guy should have removed it. I mean obviously
assuming that the guy had the ability to remove it,
okay. על בגדו ונשרף al bigdo venisraf it was on a person's
garment and the garment burnt, חייב, chayav, יחייב, yechayev, okay, because you
could say obviously you burned it. What's the חידוש? chiddush? The חידוש
chiddush is even though the other guy could have removed the coal,
what you did the act of damage, you cannot say well you
did it to yourself because you didn't remove it. You know, no,
I can allow it to burn and I'll just get you to
reimburse me. Okay, so אמר רבא תרוייהו תנינא amar Rava tarvaihu tanina
we taught both of those. על לבו דתנן al libo detnan the
case on the heart it's a משנה. Mishnah. כבשו לתוך האור kvasho
letoch ha'or if somebody you sort of held somebody down in a
in the middle of a of fire או לתוך המים o letoch
hamayim or held person's head underwater ואינו יכול לעלות משם ומת חייב
ve'eino yachol la'alot misham umet chayav and he couldn't get up, so
he that's an act of murder even if he didn't push the
guy, the guy was already in the water, he just put his
hand on the guy's head and kept the guy from going up,
he didn't even push him underwater, that's considered an act of murder
and you're חייב. chayav. Okay. דחפו לתוך האור לתוך המים dechapo letoch
ha'or letoch hamayim
however
if he pushed the guy into the fire or into the water,
even though you did the act of pushing him in, if he's
יכול לעלות משם ומת פטור yachol la'alot misham umet patur if the
guy could get out, that's not an act of murder, okay. So
the חידוש chiddush is the first case is a חידוש chiddush that's
an act of murder even though you just prevented the guy from
getting up, he was already his head was already below water. The
second case is a חידוש chiddush that it's not an act of
murder even if you pushed the guy in since he could get
out. So it's basically assumed that a person will of course naturally
act in a way to save their own lives and therefore if
they could have saved their own life and they didn't, then you
are exempt because of course you can't say I did it, the
person should have
got out of the water. Okay, however, now so that's that point
about the גחלת. gachelet. So that he says that's from that משנה.
Mishnah. Now בגדו דתנן bigdo detnan
how do you know by the case of garment that you're חייב?
chayav? Because we taught in the משנה Mishnah קרע כסותי שבר כדי
חייב. k'ra k'suti shaber kadi chayav.
If somebody says rend my garments or break my pitcher, then and
you go ahead and you listen to him, fine, he gave you
permission to do it but he didn't say you wouldn't have to
reimburse him. So you have to pay him for the garments, you
have to pay him for the picture. על מנת לפטור פטור al
mnat liftor patur but if he says no you can break my
garment, you know tear my garment and you won't have to pay
me for it, then you're exempt. So what does that tell us?
It tells us the following: that you why don't you say the
same way a person should have removed a coal from his heart,
he should have removed a coal that's burning his garment, and if
he didn't remove the coal that's burning his garment, so he brought
the injury upon himself. Yes I put the coal on the garment,
but don't blame me for it burning, a person would naturally remove
something from their garment. So this משנה Mishnah shows us that no,
that when it comes to a person's objects as opposed to a
person's body, you do not interpret things as if he is like
okay with the damage and waiving payment. If I tell you tear
my garment, tear my clothes, we don't say oh you told me
I could tear your clothes it means I wouldn't have to pay.
No, it means sometimes I allow my things to be destroyed but
I'm still going to expect you to pay me back for them.
Okay, unless I explicitly exempt you. And it's not necessarily true though
that I would naturally remove my coal from the garment. I if
I knew that I was going to get reimbursed, right, I wouldn't.
When it's my own life, of course I'm going to save my
own life. But if it's if you're burning my my clothes, you
know I figure like sometimes people will say like steal the car
I need the insurance money. You know if you're burning my clothes,
great, you know you'll pay me back, I'll be able to buy
myself a new one. So you cannot say that my absence of
removing the coal means oh I'm okay with the fact it's destroyed
and you're not going to have to pay. You know when it's
my things, it could be that I let you destroy them with
the expectation that it'll get reimbursed and ultimately you're the one who
did it, yes.
It's a bit of a logical fallacy there which is that if
we assume that someone instinctively does all they can to save their
own life, the person died meaning it was impossible for them to
save.
You mean why don't we just say the fact that they didn't
shows us that the person actually was not able to? Right, yeah
it's a good question, like how do you determine what does it
mean was able to? Like in whose estimation, right?
Yeah, we assume that he was able to.
Yeah, you're right. I mean, you know, you could imagine a case
where a person was sort of stand- it's like suicidal or whatever,
but
it's a good question. You're right. Like, I mean, how do we
know who gets to determine whether it was possible or not? I
mean, but what's one thing I think if somebody's in the middle
of a building in flames, if a guy has a little coal
on his heart and he's not doing anything and he's just lying
there, but who knows, you know, maybe he's paralyzed with fear, right?
So I mean,
right, or whatever.
It's a good question, it's a good question. Yeah.
Since we made an exception for he's trying to save his own
life, why don't we interpret flipping over in mid-air so as not
to injure himself, so as not to injure himself, on the- as
an acceptable thing?
No, no, no. So the question isn't that he did something wrong
by the flipping over in the mid-air. I mean, you know, I
mean, that's an interesting question, right? Can I intentionally cause injury to
somebody else to save my own life? Maybe actually, you know, there's
a- we'll get to actually a case actually similar to that later
on. But let's even if he did something that was acceptable, it
wasn't- it wasn't wrong to do it. Nevertheless, you know, it doesn't
mean you don't have to pay the consequences of it and pay
the damages. But you're right, the- that's what I was sort of
saying, the intentionality להזיק lehazik for בושת boshet does not mean that
you want to do an evil act, right? It's just you're doing
a conscious act that you know will cause injury. So that seems
sufficient. Okay, so now with that distinction we have one last case.
בעי רבה, Ba'ei Rava, so רבה Rava asked, הניח גחלת על לב
עבדו מהו? hiniach gachelet al lev avdo mahu? Let's say you've got
your slave and תוספות Tosafot says that the case would be that
the slave would be bound, the slave can't do anything about it,
because of course if the slave was not bound, the slave would
take the coal off of his own heart. Okay, but the slave
can't do anything. The question is about you. Okay, somebody went ahead
and put a coal on the slave and the slave is bound
and can't do anything, but you can remove it. כגופו דמי? kegufo
dami? So is sort of- do you treat the slave like your
own self? And of course you would never tolerate, you know, having-
letting the slave's life be taken, you know, in this process, and
therefore you can't blame the guy who put the coal on the
heart because of course the owner should remove it, the same way
the owner would never tolerate it if it was on his own
heart. או כממונו דמי? o kemamono dami? Or is it like on
his garment? It's like, okay, you destroy my slave, you pay me
for a new slave, right? So that's a really interesting question, right?
This gets to the whole heart of the issue, excuse the pun.
Anyway, the heart of the issue of, you know, about a slave
as property. How does the owner treat the slave? Does he treat
the slave like a piece of property, so you destroy my slave,
you'll buy me a new one, and therefore I don't have- you
know, it's not expected that I would remove the coal? Or no,
the owner recognizes that it's a human being and recognizes the life
of the slave and therefore of course he would remove the coal?
And if he doesn't, then it's his fault, not your fault. Okay.
אם תימצי לומר כגופו דמי, im timtzi lomar kegufo dami, now let's
say you say he does treat it like his own body, שורו
מהו? shoro mahu? Let's say he has a- put a coal on
an ox and a bound ox. Okay, so does- does the owner
say, well, you know, fine, you'll buy me another ox. He treats
it like a piece of property and therefore you're to blame because
there was not an expectation that the owner would remove it? Right.
Or do you say, no, an ox is still a living thing?
And if it's a living thing, then you could say, okay, I
know I put the coal on the ox, but of course the
owner was going to remove it and who wouldn't remove it from-
from a- you know, from- if their animal's about to be killed?
So- so the גמרא Gemara says, הדר פשטה, hadar pashata, so מהו?
mahu? What's the
הלכה? halacha? הדר פשטה, Hadar pashata, and he concluded: עבדו כגופו שורו
כממונו. avdo kegufo shoro kemamono. His slave he treats like his own
body and therefore it's of course taken for granted that the person
would remove a coal from his body, he'd remove a coal from
the slave, if he doesn't he is just welcoming the damage upon
himself, and therefore you're פטור. patur. And in the case, though, about
the ox, in the end of the day, it might be understand-
he- we wouldn't necessarily expect that he would remove it, maybe he
would be okay with the ox being killed as long as he's
going to be reimbursed. So really interesting question, right? About how a
person treats things that in- legally are his property, but there's a
difference between inanimate, living things that are his property, and human beings
that are his property, and does he sort of- and how does
he look at them? Does he look at them purely just as,
you know, in terms of their dollar value and purely as pieces
of property? Yes.
רש"י Rashi seems to- I mean, I'm sorry, you mentioned תוספות Tosafot
says he was כפות, kafut, but רש"י Rashi doesn't seem to have
that case, so the question is does the עבד eved have to
die?
Right, so that's a straight- right, but תוספות's Tosafot read is a
much better read of the גמרא Gemara because what type of a
question is it, of course a slave would remove something? And yeah,
so I was reading it through תוספות, Tosafot, right. Okay. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says- so that was an interesting little ending
of that. Now we move on to הדרן עלך כיצד הרגל. Hadran
Alach Keitzad HaRegel. Now we move on to the next פרק, perek,
which is gonna sort of be an interesting intersection of some discussions
of אדם המזיק adam hamazik and בור. bor. So let's take a
look. המניח את הכד ברשות הרבים, hameniach et hakad birshut harabim,
somebody puts a vessel in the middle of the public domain, ובא
אחר ונתקל בה, uva acher venitkal bah, and somebody else comes and
trips over it. So ראובן Reuven puts a vessel in the middle
of רשות הרבים reshut harabim and שמעון Shimon comes and trips on
it ושיברה, vshibra, and he broke it, פטור. patur. So שמעון Shimon
is exempt. even after, now this is of course in direct contrast
to saying a minute ago that אדם מועד לעולם. Adam muad l'olam.
אדם מועד לעולם, Adam muad l'olam, but שמעון Shimon now walks in
רשות הרבים Reshus Harabim and breaks ראובן Reuven's vessel, he doesn't have
to pay. ואם הוזק בה, V'im huzak bo, and if however שמעון
Shimon got damaged by breaking the vessel, so בעל החבית חייב בנזקו.
Ba'al hachavis chayav b'nisko. The owner of the barrel has to pay,
has to pay, ראובן Reuven has to pay שמעון Shimon because ראובן
Reuven made a בור. bor. So you understand ראובן Reuven put his
pitcher or barrel in רשות הרבים, Reshus Harabim, he made a בור
bor ב'רשות הרבים, b'Reshus Harabim, he's חייב chayav if שמעון Shimon gets
damaged, but if שמעון Shimon damages the thing, שמעון Shimon is פטור.
patur. So on the one hand a בור, bor, we understand why
he's חייב, chayav, but we don't understand why שמעון Shimon is פטור,
patur, because we said אדם מועד לעולם. Adam muad l'olam. Okay, so
let's take a look at what the גמרא Gemara does. פתח בכד
וסיים בחבית. Pasach b'kad v'siyem b'chavis.
So the first thing the גמרא Gemara notices is that it says
you put a כד, kad, a pitcher, and then it ends with
talking about the person who put the חבית, chavis, the barrel. ותנן
נמי, U'snan nami, and we have similarly where the משנה Mishnah alternates
between כד kad and חבית. chavis. זה בא בחביתו וזה בא בקורתו,
Zeh bo b'chaviso v'zeh bo b'koraso, two people are walking in רשות
הרבים, Reshus Harabim, one guy with a beam and the other guy
with a barrel. נשברה כדו של זה בקורתו של זה, Nishbera kado
shel zeh b'koraso shel zeh, and this guy's pitcher breaks on this
guy's beam. פטור, Patur, you're exempt. So פתח בחבית, pasach b'chavis, it
starts by describing the case of one guy carrying a barrel, וסיים
בכד, v'siyem b'kad, and it ends by the guy carrying a pitcher.
ותנן נמי, U'snan nami, we saw another משנה. Mishnah. זה בא בחביתו
של יין וזה בא בכדו של דבש, Zeh bo b'chaviso shel yayin
v'zeh bo b'kado shel devash, this guy's carrying a barrel of wine,
the other guy's carrying a pitcher of honey. נסדקה חבית של דבש,
Nisdeka chavis shel devash, so the pitcher of honey, of the barrel,
now he's switched to barrel, the barrel of honey cracks and the
honey is about to go to waste. And honey is a lot
more expensive, you know, per ounce than wine. So this guy decided
he'll do a favor to the other person, ושפך זה יינו והציל
את הדבש, v'shafach zeh yeino v'hitzil es hadevash, he poured out his
wine and he saved the honey in his barrel. לתוכו, l'socho, and
now he wants to be reimbursed because I did you a favor,
I saved your valuable honey. אין לו אלא שכרו, Ein lo ela
secharo, he only gets paid the fee for the service for like
the act of, you know, of saving the honey, like a hired
hand, but he does not get paid for his loss of wine.
Alright, which one wonders if that's good public policy, but anyway, that's
not our issue right now. What our issue right now is פתח
בכד וסיים בחבית. pasach b'kad v'siyem b'chavis. It initially describes the guy
had a כד, kad, a pitcher of honey, and it ends by
talking about a חבית, chavis, a barrel of honey. So clearly the
משנה Mishnah thinks the word pitcher and barrel are interchangeable, but they
are different things. So אמר רב פפא, amar Rav Pappa, היינו כד
היינו חבית. hainu kad hainu chavis. You're right, for the משנה's Mishnah's
language a כד kad and a חבית chavis refer to the same
thing, presumably a חבית chavis because the other part is always talking
about a חבית, chavis, a barrel. But למאי נפקא מינה, l'mai nafqah
minah, so why is it sort of interchanging the words, what's an
implication of knowing that these can refer to the same thing? למקח
וממכר, L'mikach u'mimkar, for case of business. You basically agree with somebody
I'm going to buy a barrel's worth of, a חבית's chavis's worth
of honey, we'll do the honey case, and he goes and he
delivers you a pitcher's worth of honey. Okay, so he could say,
well I know you said חבית, chavis, but you know, I understood
חבית chavis meant a pitcher, or the reverse, you know, you
know, he... what would be the case? You sell a pitcher, whatever.
Anyway, you can keep on... you can claim you said one but
you meant the other. So the גמרא Gemara says היכי דמי, heichi
dami, what's the case? אילימא באתרא דכדא לא קרו חביתא וחביתא לא
קרו כדא. Ilima b'asra d'kada lo karu chavisa v'chavisa lo karu kada.
If it's a place that's not like whoever the, you know, like
the משנה's Mishnah's was assuming, a place where it's very clear that
barrel means barrel and pitcher means pitcher, הלא לא קרו לה, halo
lo karu lah, you can't claim it meant the other thing. It
doesn't matter what it says in the משנה. Mishnah. In this place,
חבית chavis means חבית chavis and כד kad means כד. kad. So
הלא לא קרו לה. halo lo karu lah. אלא לא צריכא דרובא
קרו ליה לכדא כדא ולחביתא חביתא. Ela lo tzricha d'ruba karu leih
l'kada kada u'l'chavisa chavisa.
No, here would be the case. Case would be, you know, and
presumably if everybody meant the words interchangeably it also wouldn't be a
חידוש, chiddush, you know, so it must be that the words in
general have their standard meaning. A pitcher means a pitcher and a
barrel means a barrel. ואיכא נמי דקרו לחביתא כדא ולכדא חביתא. V'ika
nami d'karu l'chavisa kada u'l'kada chavisa. But
some people sometimes use the word חבית chavis to refer to a
pitcher and they use the word כד kad to refer to a
barrel. מהו דתימא זיל בתר רובא, Mahu d'teima zil basar ruba, I
might say that you go by the majority, קמשמע לן דאין הולכין
בממון אחר הרוב. kama-shma lan d'ein holchin b'mamon achar harov. You don't
go by monetary matters after the majority. What does it mean? What
principle do you go by by monetary matters? So המוציא מחבירו עליו
הראיה, Hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah, you have the burden of proof. So
the case would be, right, you paid me the money for my
pitcher, for my חבית chavis of wine, and I deliver to you
a... and I deliver to you a pitcher of wine, not a
barrel of wine. Okay, so you're saying what are you talking about?
I wanted a barrel, give me back my money, I didn't want
a pitcher. Say no, המוציא מחבירו עליו הראיה, Hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah,
I have the money now in my possession. Okay,
you prove that when we agreed to the idea of חבית chavis
we meant barrel. I understood that by חבית chavis we meant a
pitcher, not a barrel, and if you want to say otherwise you
have to prove it to me. Okay, and the same would be
in the reverse. You haven't paid me the money yet, right? We
said כד, kad, I delivered a כד, kad, and you're saying no,
we said כד kad but I wanted a barrel, I assumed we
meant a barrel. I said fine, give me back my money, I
don't want... Okay? I mean and I'm saying, No, no, no, we
agreed to this, pay me. I'm not gonna pay you, you know,
I say we meant the I say we meant the barrel, not
a pitcher. So whoever you're trying to get to pay up the
money, you have to prove that that's what you meant. And even
if in the majority of times it's clear that, you know, what
your interpretation is correct, since there's a minority number of circumstances that
people mean the other thing, then you cannot prove that's not enough
to be able to prove that your interpretation is the correct one
and that you can force the money out of this other person's
hand. Okay? So המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה Hamotzi mechavero alav harayah trumps
the idea of רוב. rov. Now, what I'm expecting somebody to ask
is, well, why don't we just see how much you paid? Like,
you know, you know, wouldn't the amount of money that you paid
prove what we were talking about? Right? If you paid a if
basically a pitcher is normally goes for ten dollars and a barrel
normally goes for fifty dollars, and you paid fifty dollars, shouldn't that
be sufficient proof? The majority possibility maybe isn't, but the amount of
money clearly points to what you meant. So תוספות Tosafot deals with
that, and תוספות Tosafot says, you know what, maybe it would, because
there's another גמרא Gemara that says it does. But he says there
could be scenarios where you can't prove anything from the money. Like
maybe, you know, maybe we didn't settle on the price, and I
want you know, we didn't say, you know, and I wanted I
you're trying to sell me a lot and I only wanted to
buy a little or vice versa, there could be cases. Or, let's
say we said, I will buy a hundred dollars of barrels from
you, and you delivered a hundred dollars worth of pitchers, right? So
there could be scenarios in which you can't prove it from money.
But it is worth noting that it's possible that the money can
be used as evidence. But the simple question of רוב, rov, the
majority of what those terms normally meant is would not be enough
proof to extract money from the other person. Okay? So that's one
parenthetical thing which has nothing to do with our focus on נזק,
nezek, but it's important a larger discussion in ש"ס Shas of המוציא
מחברו עליו הראיה. Hamotzi mechavero alav harayah. Now we get back to
our נזק nezek discussion. ובא אחר ונתקל בה ושיברה פטור. Uba acher
veniskal bah veshivrah patur.
Somebody came and was walking in רשות הרבים reshus harabim and broke
the pitcher, they're exempt. Now remember, this is right ever after having
said אדם מועד לעולם. adam muad l'olam. So the גמרא Gemara says
אמאי פטור? Amai patur? Why are you exempt? איבעי ליה לעיוני ומיזל.
Ibay lei l'iyuni umezal. You should look where you're going! You broke
this guy's pitcher, you should look where you're going! So אמרי דבי
רב משמיה דרב, Amri devei Rav mishmei deRav, so in the house
of רב Rav they said, the בית מדרש beis medrash of רב,
Rav, במלאה רשות הרבים כולה חביות. Bemila reshus harabim kullah chaviyos. This
guy basically filled the street with his barrels. So therefore, you know,
there was no way to get through the street without stepping on
his barrels, so therefore I'm exempt because I don't he doesn't have
a right to prevent me from walking through רשות הרבים. reshus harabim.
שמואל אמר באפילה שנו. Shmuel amar ba'afilah shanu. It's night, since it's
night, you can't look where you're going, and that's why you're exempt.
רבי יוחנן אמר בקרן זוית, Rebbi Yochanan amar bekeren zavis, בקרן זוית.
bekeren zavis. It was a around the corner. So basically,
right, how can these things always run out? Okay. Anyway, basically it's
like I guess you're putting the barrels here, so this guy, he's
looking where he's going, but you know as he sort of turns
the corner, you know, you can't like see around the corner, so
you can't anticipate what you're about to step on as you're turning
around the corner.
Okay. אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Papa, רב פפא Rav Papa said,
לא דייקא מתניתין אלא כשמואל או כרבי יוחנן. Lo dayka masnisin ella
k'Shmuel o k'Rebbi Yochanan. Our משנה mishna can only fit either like
שמואל Shmuel's read or רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan's read, the corner or
the darkness. But דאי כרב, De'ei keRav, and that's why you're exempt
because you don't normally can't see where you're going. But דאי כרב,
De'ei keRav, if it's the case of רב, Rav, that the רשות
הרבים reshus harabim is filled with barrels and you have to, you
know, you have no choice but to go through them, מאי איריא
נתקל? mai irya niskal? Why does it say if you tripped on
it you're exempt? אפילו שיבר נמי. Afilu shiber nami. Even if you
intentionally broke the barrel you're exempt. You don't have a right to
stop, you know, to fill up רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, I can
intentionally walk through them to get to where I have to go,
you know, you're compromising my rights of רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. So
אמר רב זביד משמיה דרבא, Amar Rav Zevid mishmei deRava, הוא הדין
דאפילו שיבר. hu hadin de'afilu shiber. No, no, no, we could read
the משנה mishna like רב, Rav, that the street was completely blocked
with these barrels, and yes it's true, if you intentionally broke them
you'd also be exempt. והאי דקתני נתקל, Vehai dekatani niskal, so why
does it say you tripped? איידי דבעי למיתני סיפא ואם הוזק בה
בעל חבית חייב בנזקו, Aidi deba'ei l'misni seifa ve'im huzak bah ba'al
chavis chayav binizko, because we're going to say that if you tripped
and got injured, the owner of the barrel has to pay you
for damages, that case is דוקא נתקל, davka niskal, only if it
was an accidental tripping. אבל שיבר, Aval shiber, if you intentionally broke
the barrel to get through, לא, lo, you cannot come to the
owner and say oh I got hurt while I was breaking your
barrel trying to get through. Why? מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? הוא דאזיק
אנפשיה. Hu d'azik anafshei. If you're intentionally breaking it, yes you have
a right to break it and you don't have to compensate the
guy, he had no right to fill the street, but if you
are knowing that you're breaking it, then you have to be careful
not to hurt yourself if you're consciously breaking it, and if you
hurt yourself in that process, don't come to me, but if you
tripped on it, then I would have to. to pay you. Okay?
So let's take a moment and pause here for a second. There's
two very interesting things that emerge here. Number one is when you
fill רשות הרבים, Reshus Harabbim, I have a right to intentionally break
the stuff to get through, okay? And we're going to see about
that in a moment, that principle. Basically it's like, you know, what
do you mean I have a right to break it and get
through? You know, let's say we had a case like this, your
car was across the road. Would I be allowed to go ahead
and like break your car down and pull it out? No, I'd
have to call the cops, right, if there was a problem. So
this is going to be an interesting discussion of עביד איניש דינא
לנפשיה. avid inish dina l'nafshei. You might not have a right to
do that, you might have to, you know, but why do I
have a right to take the law into my own hands and
to break it to get through? Why shouldn't we have to like
call the authorities and force you to remove them, right? So that's
an interesting thing number one which we're going to get to. The
assumption that if your רשות הרבים Reshus Harabbim filled with these things,
I can break them in order to get through, intentionally break them.
But the other thing, the more immediate issue is the גמרא's Gemara
assumption that if I break your barrel I should pay because I
should watch where I'm going, and it gives scenarios that, oh, I'm
not expected to watch where I'm going because it's nighttime, it's around
the corner, or whatever. But the question is, why does any of
this make sense? Whatever happened to אדם מועד לעולם? adam muad l'olam?
Right? So who cares? I should watch where I'm going, I shouldn't
watch where I'm going, I should be חייב chayav even in the
nighttime, I should be חייב chayav even around the corner. Why does
the גמרא Gemara even say, you know, I should watch where I'm
going or I shouldn't watch where I'm going? Whatever happened to אדם
מועד לעולם? adam muad l'olam? So it's very strange that the גמרא
Gemara seems to not to accept the idea that I am exempt,
it's not bothered with the concept of אדם מועד לעולם, adam muad
l'olam, and the only question it has is not that I should
pay because I should always be liable, but I should pay because
I should have watched where I was going, that I had negligence,
I should've been paying attention, and it has to give me examples
where that's not expected for me to be able to see what
I'm doing.
Is this in רשות הרבים? Reshus Harabbim? Why... so why would he
be...
Ah, so what you're saying is is that since the guy who
put the barrel did something wrong, that should get me off, and
that's... so that's probably the best answer, but let's take a look.
I wanted to put that out there. I want to read another
line and then I'll tell you what תוספות Tosafos and the רמב"ן
Ramban say about this. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this,
אמר ליה רבי אבא, Amar lei Rabbi Abba,
קתני רישא נתקל, katani reisha nitkal,
okay, אמר ליה רבי אבא לרב אשי, Amar lei Rabbi Abba l'Rav
Ashi, רבי אבא Rabbi Abba said to רב אשי, Rav Ashi, הכי
אמרי במערבא, Hachi amri b'maarava,
here's what they say in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, משמיה דרב עולא
mishmei d'Rav Ulla in the name of, or some say רבי אלעאי
Rabbi Ilai because normally it's just עולא Ulla not רב עולא, Rav
Ulla, לפי שאין דרכן של בני אדם להתבונן בדרכים. lefi she'ein darkan
shel bnei adam l'hitbonen b'drachim.
No, actually, you don't have to say it's nighttime, you don't have
to say it was around the corner, the whole point of the
משנה Mishna is to tell you is that people don't look where
they're going, okay? Yeah, people are, you know, constantly they're... they're in
their own heads and whatever, and you have to understand that people
don't look where they're going and that's why you're פטור. patur. הוה
עובדא בנהרדעא, Hava uvda b'nahardea, so there's a case in נהרדעא Nahardea
that somebody broke a barrel in רשות הרבים Reshus Harabbim and it
wasn't nighttime and it wasn't around the corner, okay? וחייב שמואל v'chiyev
Shmuel
and שמואל Shmuel made him pay because he said you should've watched
where, you know, you should watch where you're going if it's not
one of those special cases. בפומבדיתא B'pumbedita it happened... הוה עובדא hava
uvda in פומבדיתא B'pumbedita וחייב רבא v'chiyev Rava or רבה Rabbah and
רבא Rava made him pay. So the גמרא Gemara says בשלמא שמואל
כשמעתיה, bishlama Shmuel k'shmatia, I understand why שמואל Shmuel made him pay
because שמואל's Shmuel going to the explanation, שמואל Shmuel says you're only
פטור patur at nighttime, in the daytime you should watch where you're
going. אלא רבא, ela Rava, רבא Rava who exempted him, לימא כשמואל
סבירא ליה, leima k'Shmuel s'vira lei, maybe he agrees like שמואל, Shmuel,
okay, that basically says that normally in the daytime you would be
חייב, chayav, you need a special circumstances like the night, because here
he said you were חייב, chayav, so it sounds like the normal...
that's the normal position. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רב פפא,
amar Rav Papa, no, קרנא דעצרא הוה. karna d'atzra hava. No, no,
no, this was a special case where people should know that to
look out. Why?
רש"י Rashi says this is also around the corner, but it's a
special case means it was a time when they were pressing the
olives. So it was like and in the time when they're pressing
the olives and it's right in front of the olive press, it's
very common for people to leave these pitchers of olive oil, or
I guess the pitchers that they're going to be filling with the
olive oil, right in the street right outside the olive press, okay?
דכיון דברשות קעבדי d'keivan d'bireshut ka avdi and since it's known that
that's what happens and people have the permission to be leaving their
pitchers there, in that case איבעי ליה לעיוני ומיזל, ibai lei l'iyunei
u'meizal, you should watch where you're going. So here a case it
is, it was a case of a daytime as opposed to the
משנה Mishna that says you're פטור. patur. They would say that in
the case of a day... in the first position, שמואל Shmuel would
say that in case of a daytime, a normal case you'd be
חייב, chayav, you should watch where you're going. And you could say
the other position of רבא Rava is you could say no, no,
no, in general we'll say like they say in ארץ ישראל, Eretz
Yisrael, people aren't expected to watch where they're going and in general
you're פטור. patur. Okay? But there's some cases where you are expected
to watch where you're going. You know that it's the time of
the pressing of the olive oil and you know... You know that
it's the time of the pressing of the olive oil and you
know that you're getting near the olive press, so of course there
you have to watch what you're doing. In general you're not expected
to watch where you're going, but in these types of circumstances where
people have a permission to be doing things in the street, then
you should have known to watch where you were going. Okay, so
the bottom line, the upshot of all of this is
what seems to be exactly against what we said yesterday, right? Which
seems to be there's a presumption that even as an אדם המזיק,
adam hamazik, you're going to be exempt unless you have some degree
of fault and some degree of negligence. So either we have to
say that you're not expected to watch where you're going, so you
have no fault, or you are expected to watch where you're going
and therefore you do have fault, unless it's a special case like
it's nighttime or it's around the corner or whatever. But basically the
common denominator, whether we assume people are or are not supposed to
watch where they're going or cases where everybody should watch like it's
the time of the pressing of the oil, the common denominator of
all of this is that a person is not liable for damage
that they do unless there's a certain degree of negligence and a
certain degree of fault. And how does that fit with what we
said before that אדם מועד לעולם? adam muad l'olam? So there are
two basic answers of the ראשונים rishonim in this.
תוספות, Tosafot, which is I assume the less interesting one, and the
רמב''ן, Ramban, which is the more interesting one. תוספות Tosafot's answer is,
well, when we say אדם מועד לעולם, adam muad l'olam, we don't
really mean לעולם. l'olam. Okay, what we really mean is, תוספות Tosafot
basically has a continuum of degree of negligence. Okay, so you basically
have here which is like full פשיעה peshia that a שומר חינם
shomer chinam would be חייב chayav for. Okay, that's full negligence, right?
Remember the גמרא Gemara called that like רוח מצויה. ruach metzuya. Okay,
and then you have at the other end of the extreme you
have אונס, ones, right? Completely act of God, you know, absolutely no
negligence. And then in the middle of this continuum you have
גניבה ואבידה. gneiva v'aveida. Something gets lost or stolen, right? That's a
שומר שכר shomer sachar is חייב chayav for that. That's a middle—well,
let me put that down. Okay. גניבה ואבידה. gneiva v'aveida.
Okay, so that's like, that's like, you know, a middle degree of
negligence. This is full negligence and this is partial negligence. Partial. Because,
you know, you could have watched it better to prevent it from
getting stolen or lost. Okay, so there's a partial negligence in that
case. And here—so there's some, you could have done more. Within גניבה
ואבידה, gneiva v'aveida, of course,
אבידה aveida is much closer to the full negligence, right? Things get
lost means you were really being sloppy with them. Okay, so getting
stolen, somebody else was coming and trying to take it, was much
closer to the אונס ones side. All right. So תוספות Tosafot says
when we say אדם adam is מועד לעולם, muad l'olam, we mean
that you're חייב chayav not only in a case of פשיעה, peshia,
you're even חייב chayav in these—in the cases of partial negligence that
are on this side of פשיעה. peshia. But cases where you have
zero—like we have zero negligence or very minimal negligence, these are cases
that you're going to be פטור patur on. And that's the idea
of walking in רשות הרבים reshut harabbim where you'd basically say if
you're not expected to watch where you're going, then it's considered to
be very minimal type of negligence. Okay, so for תוספות Tosafot we're
not saying מועד לעולם. muad l'olam. We are not saying all of
this. We are actually saying that you—based on our סוגיא sugya what
we're actually saying is, you need a small degree of negligence to
be—you need some degree of
negligence to be חייב, chayav, but if it's only a very—but if
it's only a very small degree, you're actually—you're actually going to be
פטור. patur. Now, why תוספות Tosafot didn't just say that you're חייב
chayav in these cases, but and is because for example to say
that you don't have to watch where you're going is not really
an אונס, ones, right? I mean obviously, you know, there's a certain
degree you could be more careful even if in general people don't
watch where they're going or whatever. And there are other סוגיות sugyot
as well that basically lead תוספות Tosafot to say you need, you
know, you're חייב chayav in cases of what do you call it,
of partial negligence, but if the negligence is very small you're going
to be פטור patur and you're not really חייב לעולם. chayav l'olam.
Okay, so that's תוספות. Tosafot. תוספות Tosafot says אדם מועד לעולם adam
muad l'olam doesn't really mean—I don't—doesn't really mean לעולם. l'olam. תוספות Tosafot
says אדם מועד לעולם adam muad l'olam just means that you're—that you
don't need full negligence to be חייב, chayav, but you still need
partial negligence. The רמב''ן Ramban's answer is a much more interesting one.
The רמב''ן Ramban says, and this is what Hillel was saying, the
רמב''ן Ramban said and I think I've said this before, yes you
are מועד לעולם, muad l'olam, assuming that there is not contributory negligence.
So if I went ahead, the רמב''ן Ramban says when the גמרא
Gemara says that if a רוח מצויה—I ruach metzuya remember it said
the case that a person is חייב chayav by a רוח שאינה
מצויה. ruach she'eina metzuya. The רמב''ן Ramban says even if like a
whirlwind picked me up and threw me down on your vessels or
whatever and I broke them, I'd be חייב, chayav, אדם מועד לעולם,
adam muad l'olam, complete אונס ones I'm חייב. chayav. So what's going
on in this case of רשות הרבים reshut harabbim that I'm פטור
patur if I'm not supposed to watch where I'm going, not expected
to watch where I'm going? Because you're also negligent. If you know
people usually don't watch where they're going and you're putting your vessels
in רשות הרבים, reshut harabbim, then you're bringing it upon yourself. So
therefore what?
Well, sort of לפני עיוור lifnei iver I guess, but you're you're
I mean, yes, לפני עיוור lifnei iver means that I'm making you
do like okay, but I don't know if I'd exactly say it's
לפני עיוור lifnei iver if I trip and I get hurt. If
I trip and I break your thing, you know, but yeah, but
in contributory negligence when you're bringing it upon yourself, that's what happens
here. So in the רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, when I'm choosing to
put my vessel down, you know, you'd be חייב chayav even though
you have no negligence, but because I know that normally you don't
watch where you're going and I'm going to put it down anyway,
I am welcome, I am bringing it upon myself. If you normally
do watch where you're going, that doesn't make the the issue of
you watching where you're going isn't that I needed your negligence for
you to be חייב. chayav. If you watch where you're going, it
means that I'm not negligent for putting it down because I could
expect that you will see it. So the whole גמרא'ס Gemara's discussion
about should the guy, is the guy expected to watch where he's
going, is it the nighttime, is it around the corner, whatever, is
not to determine if the מזיק mazik had negligence. We don't need
the מזיק's mazik negligence. It's to determine if the ניזק nizak was
negligent in putting it down because he should have realized that it
was likely given the way people act and where the thing was
placed, it was likely to get damaged. Yes, Jenna.
It's almost like laws around reasonable expectations of privacy but like the
same act of you dropping or whatever something that you would do
in someone's private house
it's
illegal for you to do but if they're in the middle of
the street and they're talking about something then they don't have a
reasonable expectation.
That's a nice point. Right, exactly. It's a nice point. Yes.
What about when he intentionally breaks it even though it's contributory negligence
what about the intention to break it?
So that we're going to get to, but that's if I did
something actually that's going to be taking the law into your own
hands when your stuff is in the way.
Do we have that?
Yes, so we're going to get to that. But that's when the
stuff was in the way and I needed to break it to
get through. Okay, but as opposed but in this case where it
was just I didn't need to break it to get through it
was just an accident, right, that would be the but we'll see
the case. Okay, so that's like this is like amazing like the
גמרא Gemara says אדם מועד לעולם Adam muad l'olam and right after
saying אדם מועד לעולם Adam muad l'olam and falling off a rooftop
with a רוח שאינה מצויה ruach she'eina m'tzuyah and all these things,
it thinks about oh, but you know, if you don't have to
watch where you're going you should be פטור. patur. So that leads
תוספות Tosafot to radically redefine מועד לעולם muad l'olam and say you
need a certain degree of negligence. And רמב״ן Ramban says no no
no no. You are מועד לעולם. muad l'olam. You fall off a
rooftop, a whirlwind pushes you off, you're חייב. chayav. I don't care.
If the guy though knew that you would have acted in certain
ways and he put it in your way, right, then he's to
blame as well and that's why you're פטור. patur. Alright so let's
do one more piece of גמרא. Gemara.
Okay. איבעיא להו, Iba'ya lehu, they asked the following question. Sorry. שלח
ליה רב חסדא לרב נחמן, Shlach lei Rav Chisda l'Rav Nachman, רב
חסדא Rav Chisda sent to רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. הרי אמרו, Harei
amru, they said לרכובה שלוש. l'rechuva shalosh.
If somebody pushes somebody like with his like a leg, you know,
then he the בושת boshet is an embarrassment worth like three
זוז. zuz. Okay. לבעיטה חמישה, l've'itah chamishah, he pays five זוז. zuz.
This is like this is like a standard fines that they had
for רש״י Rashi says for בושת, boshet, you know, if people that
they assessed that that was the degree of embarrassment. ולסנוקרת שלוש עשרה,
u'l'sanokeret shelosh esreh,
but if you and hit him with like a this thing which
is basically a like a saddle, you pay thirteen. לפנדא דמרא ולקופינא
דמרא מאי? l'panda d'mara u'l'kufina d'mara mai?
What about if it was like the handle of a hoe or
the metal of a hoe? How much would you pay for embarrassment
if somebody did that to someone? שלח ליה Shlach lei he sent
back to him, חסדא חסדא, Chisda Chisda, קנסא קמגבית בבבל? knasa ka'magbit
b'Vavel? חסדא, Chisda, what are you doing? Are you collecting קנס knas
in בבל? Bavel? בושת boshet is a type of a קנס knas
payment, something we'll discuss later, okay, whether it's קנס knas or it's
like קנס, knas, but anyway and you don't do it unless you
have סמיכה, smicha, unless you have that סמיכה smicha that goes back
to משה רבינו. Moshe Rabbeinu. You don't do it in בבל. Bavel.
אימא לי גופא דעובדא היכי הוה? Eima li gufa d'uvda heichi hava?
Tell me exactly what the story was. Let me get to the
bottom of this. שלח ליה Shlach lei he sent him, דהוה גרגותא,
De'hava garguta, a certain well דבי תרי d'vei terei of two of
a partnership owned by partners. דכל יומא הוה דלי חד מינייהו, d'chol
yoma hava dali chad mineihu,
they would alternate days, each day a different person would draw the
water. אתא חד קא דלי ביומא דלא דיליה, Ata chad ka dali
b'yoma d'la deilei, one person came and was drawing the water when
it wasn't his day. אמר ליה Amar lei so the other guy
said, יומא דידי הוא, Yoma didi hu, it's my day. ואשגח ביה,
v'ashgach bei, the other guy ignored it. Ah, whatever shut up and
he was drawing water when he wasn't allowed to. שקל פנדא דמרא
shakal panda d'mara so the guy whose day it was took the
like the handle of a hoe, ומחיה v'machyei and he hit him.
Okay, to protect his access to the water on his day. אמר
ליה Amar lei so he wanted to know what should I do
to fine this guy? He beat this other person who was drawing
from the well on the wrong day. אמר ליה Amar lei so
he said back to him, who was it? רב נחמן Rav Nachman
said to רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, מאה פנדי בפנדא למחיה, Me'ah pandei
b'panda l'machyei, let him hit him a hundred times with the handle,
אפילו גוונא דהאי Afilu gavna d'hai he hit him with the handle.
He shouldn't be paying anything. He had a right to.
even according to the opinion that you're not allowed to take the
law into your own hands, but במקום פסידא עביד איניש דינא לנפשיה,
bimkom pseida avid inish dina lenafsheih, but if it's going to be
an irrevocable loss, you are allowed to take the law into your
own hands. Now, why was it an irrevocable loss? Let him draw
the water and then let me sue him to be reimbursed.
So רש״י Rashi says, well you don't know, I mean like my
plant might have died, what's going to happen to my plants today
if I can't get them watered? What's going to happen to, maybe
the well will run dry after a certain period of time? So
my ability, if I really am going to suffer a loss that
cannot be recovered in the courts, I'm allowed to take the law
into my own hands. But if it can be recovered in the
courts, then I am not. Okay, and the reason we are bringing
this in here is because that's going to be the case of
filling a רשות הרבים reshus harabbim with pitchers. Am I allowed to
break my way through? Why don't I have to call the cops?
Why am I allowed to take the law my own hands and
break my way through? So this introduces what we're going to discuss
tomorrow, this very important סוגיא sugya of basically he calls it vigilantism,
but it's taking the law into your own hands to protect loss
of your own property or to protect your own rights. Vigilantism, right,
that's like Spider-Man, right, that's like vigilantism is you're trying to stop
other people from doing crimes, whatever, in general in society. Taking the
law into your own hands is protecting your own property and your
own rights, rather than letting injury happen and then trying to recover
it through going to בית דין Beis Din or through calling the
cops. So that's what we're going to discuss in this context of
filling the road with barrels. But again, the key חידוש chiddush that
we said today about אדם מועד לעולם adam muad l'olam is there's
a debate should you watch where you're going, should you not watch
where you're going and so on, but is that because you are
only liable if you're negligent? Or is that because no, no, no,
you're liable all the time whether you're negligent or not, but the
issue is whether the other person was negligent. Should they have been
aware that they were going, that by putting their pitcher there, you
were going to trip on it and therefore they were bringing it
upon themselves? Okay, so two very different interpretations of the limits of
אדם מועד לעולם. adam muad l'olam.